Let us now learn a little bit about CSS preprocessors,
现在让我们来学习一些 CSS 预处理器 相关的知识
in particular about Less and Sass.
尤其是 Less 和 Sass 的相关知识
When you go to the Bootstrap website,
当你进入 Bootstrap 的网站时
you will notice that they mention that Bootstrap is built using Less.
你可能会发现他们说 Bootstrap 是用 Less 来搭建的
And they also have a Sass port.
他们也会提供一个 Sass 端口
And, at that point, you must be wondering, what is this Less?
然后你可能就会想 什么是 Less？
What is Sass?
Sass 又是什么？
And how do they play a role in defining the bootstraps CSS classes?
这俩货在定义 Bootstrap 的 CSS 类时 起到了什么作用？
Let's learn a little bit about these CSS preprocessors, now.
现在就让我们学一些这方面的知识
You have learned a lot about CSS in the previous course.
你已经学了很多 CSS 的相关知识了
Now, CSS is wonderful for styling and
所以你应该知道 CSS 是一个绝佳的
defining various properties of HTML LMX.
拿来定义各种 HTML 元素属性的东西
But when you look at CSS, CSS is rather limited
但是当实际运用 CSS 时 你可能会发现 它有许多限制
when it comes to being like a typical programming language.
你不能像编写典型的编程语言代码那样 去编写 CSS 代码
CSS doesn't support things like variables, nesting, expressions, or even functions.
CSS 并不支持变量 嵌套 表达式和函数
Now, adding all these things in place would
所以如果这些功能都能加进 CSS 的话
definitely benefit people who write CSS code.
CSS 无疑会好用得多
And also, without the availability of these features,
而且除去好用这一因素
the maintainability of CSS suffers a lot.
缺少这些功能的 CSS 是很难维护的
For people who are very well used to programming, you can't live
如果你经常写代码的话 你可能就能体会到
without things like variables, functions, expressions and so on.
没有变量 函数和表达式是多么蛋疼的一件事
And that is where the downside of CSS begins to show up very quickly.
也因此 越来越多的 CSS 的弊病都 很快地暴露了出来
This is where CSS Preprocessors come to your rescue.
这时候 CSS 预处理器就显得弥足珍贵了
If you would like to write CSS more in the programming style that you're used to
如果你想让写 CSS 代码的过程更类似于 你平时写代码的过程的话
then go no further than looking at the CSS preprocessors.
强烈建议你去学学 CSS 预处理器
There are three popular CSS preprocessors that are out there.
现在比较流行的预处理器有三种
Less, Sass, and Stylus.
Less, Sass 和 Stylus
We're gonna examine Less and Sass in some detail in this lecture.
我们将会学习的是 Less 和 Sass
But there is a lot more to these preprocessors than what I can explain
不过除了我们接下来要学习的内容外
in a short duration.
CSS 预处理器还有非常多其它酷炫的功能
I will give you links to go and explore these preprocessors further.
我会提供你一些链接 这些链接可以帮助 你进行进一步的学习
Now, when you write code using one of these preprocessors the expectation
作为一个预处理器 如果我用了它来写代码的话
is that they will be automatically transformed into the equivalent CSS code.
它要能自动帮我将其转换成有用的 CSS 代码
Now this is where either compilers or
而为了做到这一点 我们通常会用
transformation tools that are available, come to your rescue.
一些编译器或是一些专门的工具
In particular, we'll examine one such tool for compiling Less code.
特别地 我们将会学习一个用来编译 Less 代码的工具
Bootstrap itself was originally designed in Less.
Bootstrap 一开始就是用 Less 写的
Now they do have a Sass port available.
而现在它也有 Sass 的端口
The typical CSS preprocessor features that are supported include variables,
一个传统的 CSS 预处理器将会支持
nesting of selectors, then mixins, and functions and expressions.
变量, 选择器的嵌套, 混入, 函数和表达式
We'll examine some of these in more detail through some examples.
我们将通过一些例子来学习其中的一些细节
And in the exercise we'll see how we can write Less code,
而在下个练习里我们将会学习 如何写 Less 代码
and automatically compile it into the corresponding CSS.
以及如何将其编译为相对应的 能用的 CSS 代码
I am presenting these features for both Less and
我将同一个功能的 Less 实现和 Sass 实现 同时放了出来
Sass side by side, so that you can see the similarities between the two.
你可以看到这两种实现非常相似
At the same time,
同一时间，
minor differences in the syntax between the two different preprocessors.
这两者的语法会有一些细小的差异
Variables can be defined both in Less and Sass.
首先它们都能定义变量
In Less, you usually precede the variable name with an @ sign
不过在 Less 里面 变量的变量名前面 是用 @ 来修饰
In Sass, you precede the variable label with a $.
而在 Sass 里面则是用 $ 来修饰
Within the code, you can use the variables just by specifying the name,
如果你想用这个变量 直接指定这个变量名
including the @, in case of Less, or including the $ in case of Sass.
然后再用 @ 或 $ 打头即可 这取决于你用 Less 还是 Sass
So in this example you can see that I have defined a color and a height variable.
在这个栗子里 我定义了一个颜色变量 和一个高度变量
And then I am using them inside my CSS classes by specifying for example,
你可以从图中看出
the background with the color variable and a height with the height variable.
我是怎么应用它们的
Variables also have scopes both in Less and Sass.
在 Less 和 Sass 中 变量是有作用域的
So if you define a variable inside the scope,
在你定义一个变量后
then the applicability of the variable is limited to that scope.
只有在相对应的作用域中 你才能调用这个变量
So if you are used to programming you understand scopes very well.
如果你平时经常编程 你对这个概念 应该不会陌生
The advantage of using the preprocessors is nesting.
用预处理器的一大好处就是你可以进行嵌套
When we write CSS code, you realize that you might be having
当我们写 CSS 代码时 你可能会发现你定义的 某个 CSS 类
certain classes that are dependent upon other classes.
需要基于你之前定义的某个类
So for example, you might have a carousel class and then inside a carousel class,
举个栗子 你可能会写一个 carousel 类
you might have an item class.
然后在 carousel 类里面 你可能又定义了 一个 item 类
Now when you write that CSS code, you will write .carousal and
如果你是用 CSS 代码来写的话 你将会写一个 .carousel
then you will have another one for .carousel dot item, and so on.
和一个 .carousel .item 之类的
Nesting allows you to nest the classes.
嵌套则允许你进行类的嵌套
So that you have a parent class and
意味着你定义的每一个类
then the subclasses going inside that parent classes.
都可以有父类和子类
In this this example I have shown you both Less and
在这个栗子里 我同时用 Less 和 Sass
Sass's way of defining nesting.
写了一个嵌套
They pretty much are similar in nature when they define nesting.
它们在定义嵌套时非常相似
So here, I am having a carousel class.
你可以看到我在这写了一个 carousel 类
And inside the carousel class, I have an item class.
然后在 carousel 类里面 我直接写了一个 item 类
And inside that height class, I have an image class.
然后在这个 item 类里面 我还写了一个 image 类
So the properties that I defined to the image class are applicable
注意 在这里这个 image 类中的这些属性
only to the images that are inside a carousel item element.
是只给 carousel item 中的 image 设置的
Very often, you might have certain CSS classes, and then you might define other
我们在写 CSS 类时经常碰到的另一个问题 就是重用问题
CSS classes that share similar properties with the previous CSS classes.
也就是说我们可能会想重复使用某些 特定的 CSS 样式
Now, if you go with standard CSS, you will have to define them separately.
如果你直接去写 CSS 代码的话 你需要逐个地去定义
With mixins, what happens is that if you have a group of properties,
不过当你有了混入时 重用就变得非常简单了
CSS properties that you want to apply to several classes,
混入是用来减少重复代码的
then you can define a mixin.
非常有用的一个功能
Like, for example,
比如说在这个栗子里
in this example you can see that I have defined a mixin called the zero margin,
你可以看到我定义了一个叫 zero-margin 的混入
which contains margins as zero pixels, and then some other properties.
它定义了 margin: 0px auto; 和其它一些属性
Summed up together, they can be used inside other CSS classes.
这些属性通过混入可以直接 应用在 CSS 类里面
So they're in Less, for example, if I define the zero margin I can use that zero
比如说在 Less 里面
margin inside another CSS class by including the name as shown here.
通过 .zero-margin 来引入 zero-margin 的话
Same thing with Sass.
这个 CSS 类就会拥有 zero-margin 里面 定义的所有属性了
In Sass, when you define a mixin, you precede the name of the mixin with @mixin.
Sass 是类似的 只不过将 .zero-margin 换成 @include zero-margin 而已
And when you use a mixin inside in another class,
你可以将混入看成是一个父类
you will see @ include and then specify name of the mixin.
然后将引用混入的过程看成是继承
The advantage of using mixin's is,
使用混入的优势是
mixin's can hold multiple CSS definitions together.
混入可以同时定义多个 CSS 属性
Unlike variables, which are inapplicable to a single CSS definition.
而变量一次只能定义一个
Mixins can also take parameter values.
更炫酷的是 混入还可以接受参数
So in this example, both in Less and Sass, you can see that for my mixin,
在这个栗子里 你可以看到我在混入里面
I have two parameter values.
定义了两个参数
The padding value for the up and down padding, and
一个是拿来定义上下的填充的
another padding value for left and right padding.
另一个则是定义左右的填充
So, when I use that class inside other classes,
对应的 当我使用这些混入时
I can specify the parameters for the mixin.
就需要传进参数了
So, in Less, for example, I am using the zero margin mixin that
让我们来看看这个栗子吧
I've defined, class that I've defined with two parameters.
我们在两个类中引用了混入
And then I can use that zero margin class inside, for example, the row header class.
你可以看到我在其中一个引用时 没有传进参数
If I don't give any parameters the default values specified will be used.
这意味着混入将会使用默认的参数
Instead, if I give specific parameter values, as you see for the row content.
而如果我传进了参数的话
I specify the up and down padding as 50 pixels, and
混入就会使用我传进去的参数 50
left and right padding as zero pixels.
这一个过程貌似相当复杂
Then automatically this will be compiled into the appropriate
不过这个过程的编译会自动帮你做好
CSS class with the light padded values defined.
所以你不用担心
Sass has a slightly different syntax for defining this.
你也可以看到 左右两种实现只有一点点 语法上的差异
So again, it's basically the same way.
其它大部分都是一样的
So you can see the similarity between Less and Sass here too.
从这你也可以感受到 Less 和 Sass有多相似了
In here, when you use the mixin,
特别地 在 Sass 中使用混入时
as you see you are going to precede the mixin name with the @ include.
你需要在混入的名字前用 @include 打头
And then in brackets, you specify the parameter values.
然后再括号里传进你想传的参数
You can also do a lot of mathematical operations on the values or
你也可以在混入中
variables that you use inside Mixins.
做很多数学运算
So here, for example, I defined a variable as carousel height.
在这个栗子里 我定义了一个叫 carousel-height 的变量
In some of the classes I am using the carousel height, as are these.
然后在下面的类中我都引用了这个变量
In other classes maybe I may want to do a mathematical operation.
且在一些类中我还用这个变量 做了一些数学运算
So for example,
举例来说，
I can define a smaller class with one quarter of the parameter size.
我可以将代表“小”的类的高度设置为 carousel-height 的四分之一
A larger class would double the parameter, the variable value, and so on.
然后将代表"大"的类的高度设置为两倍
So, those can also be defined in Bootstrap.
这些同样可以定义在 Bootstrap 中
So mathematical operations give you a lot of flexibility
可以想象 数学运算的支持极大地提高了
in the way you write the Less or the Sass code.
你写 Less 和 Sass 代码的灵活性
Besides these, there are many other features that are supported by
除了我们讲过的这些 还有许多其它
both Less and Sass.
Less 和 Sass 的很棒的功能
And even stylus for that matter.
事实上 Stylus 也很不错
You have functions.
注意到我们还能用函数
So these functions allow you to do mathematical operations, list,
这些函数允许你做数学运算
string operations.
允许你操作列表和字符串
Even color operations.
甚至允许你对颜色进行操作
So, for example, you can take a color value and darken the color value.
几个栗子 你可以接收一个颜色 然后加深它并返回之
For example, if you're defining a value for a hover color.
一个实际的案例就是当你想获得 一个组件的悬浮颜色时
You can take the standard color and then automatically process it and
你通常可以接收这个组件在 平常状态下的颜色
define a darker color to be applied when you are hovering over that element.
然后将它加深来作为有鼠标悬停在其上时 显示的颜色
All this are flexibility that pre-processing language bring for us.
这些种种写代码时的灵活性都是 预处理器带给我们的
You can also import existing Less
而且 你完全可以在你的 Less 或 Sass 文件中
are Sass classes into other Less and Sass classes.
引入你之前写过的 Less 和 Sass 类
Of course, Less classes can be imported into other Less files,
引入的方法非常简单
and Sass files can be imported into other Sass files correspondingly.
直接 @import xxx 就行了
Let's pay a quick visit to the Bootstrap site to see how Less and
让我们来看看 Bootstrap 是怎么用
Sass are actually used within Bootstrap.
Less 和 Sass 的
If you go to the Bootstrap site, under CSS.
当你进入 Bootstrap 网站时 你可以找到一个
You can click on this link called Using Less.
Using Less 的链接 单击它 你就可以获得
This is where the detailed description of the less values and
Bootstrap 在 Less 用了哪些变量 混入 等等的信息
variables and mixins that are used in Bootstrap are defined in great detail.
Bootstrap 中的变量和混入是定义得 非常精细的
You can actually get hold of Bootstrap in less format and
所以如果你想更改 Bootstrap 中的某些样式 你可以尝试
then modify things and compile your own version of Bootstrap if you prefer to.
通过更改 Less 格式的 Bootstrap 来定制你自己的 Bootstrap
So, all these are available for you to define.
不过注意你的更改很可能"牵一发而动全身"
So you can see how bootstrap is defining the different color values
在这里 你可以看到 Bootstrap 是怎么通过变量 来定义不同的颜色的
using bootstrap variables, and links, and typography and so on.
你也可以看到它是怎么定义链接 排版等东西的
These are all specified as variables inside Bootstrap.
这些都是通过一个个变量来实现的
Similarly, Bootstrap also has a Sass version.
Bootstrap 同样有 Sass 版本
So they have an official Sass port now available for
它们有官方的 Sass 端口提供给你
you, which is maintained as a separate GitHub repository.
这一部分将会由一个单独的 GitHub 仓库来维护
So you can get the Sass version of Bootstrap
所以只要你的项目有需求
if that is what you are going to use within your project.
你完全可以放心地使用 Sass 版本的 Bootstrap
In the next set of courses we're going to explore more on taking
在接下来一系列的课程中 我们将会学习
Bootstrap or other CSS files in
如何将在预处理器中编写的代码
the pre-processor format and automatically generating the CSS code.
自动编译成可用的 CSS 代码
Now, we will move on to the exercise.
所以 让我们进行一个练习吧
The next exercise, we will explore the use of Less.
在这个练习里 我们会亲自去写一些 Less 代码
So we will see how we can define the Less
我们将会亲自写一些 Less 的变量
variables and mixins and nesting, and
和一些嵌套 混入
then construct a CSS file by compiling the Less code.
然后我们会把我们写的 Less 代码 转换成可用的 CSS 代码
To do this, we are going to make use of the nodes
为了做到这一点 我们会利用一个工具
support through that Less C compiler,
这个工具是可以装在你系统上的
that is a node module that can be installed on your system.
一个 node 模块 【翻译 - Carefree0910】